(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-27T02:01:54.788085",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
はい！ホロライブ2期生、大空スバルでーす！
Hi! Hololive Gen 2's Oozora Subaru here!
ということで、1級船舶免許を取ってから、なんと1年が経ちました！
It has actually been a whole year since I got my first-class boat license!
大空スバルです！
I'm Oozora Subaru!
今回はロケに来ております！
Today, we are out on location!
ゲストはミオしゃー！
Our guest is Mio-sha!
はーい！
Hello!
うち、うち、うちだよ！大神ミオだよ！ホロライブゲーマーズの大神ミオです！
It's me, me, me! Ookami Mio! I'm Ookami Mio from Hololive Gamers!
今日は来てくれてありがとう！
Thanks for coming today!
いや、呼ばれたは呼ばれたけど…
Well, I was invited, but...
今日何をするんでしょうか？
what are we doing today?
今日の企画言っちゃっていい、わけ？
Can I reveal today's project?
ああ、もうじゃあ、言っちゃってもらって…
Oh, sure, go ahead and tell me...
それでは参ります！大空スバル、いざ大海原へ！
Here we go! Oozora Subaru, heading out to the great ocean!
ミオしゃを海のドライブに連れて行く！ということで！
I'm taking Mio-sha on an ocean drive!
ええ？！
What?!
大空クルーズ第1号のお客様がミオしゃに決定しました！
Mio-sha has been chosen as the very first guest for Oozora Cruise!
いやいやいやいやいや…
No, no, no, no, no...
ガチで怖いから、ガチで！
Because it's seriously scary, seriously!
ね、大丈夫大丈夫！ガチ免許あるから！免許！
No, it's fine! I have a real license! A license!
いやいやいや、シオンと取った免許あるから大丈夫だから！
No, no, no! I have the license I got with Shion, so it's fine!
免許取りたての運転ほど怖いことねえじゃん！
There's nothing scarier than driving with a freshly licensed person!
いや、しかも1回スバル、個人的にちゃんと運転しに行ってるから！
And besides, Subaru has personally gone to drive once!
あ、練習済みってこと？
Ah, so you've already practiced?
そう！練習もしてきたから、任せてよ！
Yes! I practiced, so leave it to me!
学科の成績良かったから！
My academic grades were good, too!
しかもさ、ミオしゃと言えば釣りでしょ？
Besides, speaking of Mio-sha, it's fishing, right?
いや、そんなことないからね！
No, that's not true!
いやいや、ミオしゃと言えば釣りだから、釣りしてさ、うめえ魚でも食おうよ！
No, speaking of Mio-sha, it's fishing. Let's fish and eat some delicious fish!
おお、じゃあ、今日は船釣りするってこと？
Oh, so we're doing boat fishing today?
そう！船釣りをします！
Yes! We're doing boat fishing!
なんかスバル免許取ったんですけど、船の運転は本当に危なくて…
Even though Subaru got a license, driving a boat is really dangerous...
やめてよ、なんか不安になるようなこと言うの！
Stop saying things that make me anxious!
マジで本当に、死にたくなかったら今日見張り手伝ってほしい、本当に！
Seriously, if you don't want to die, please help me keep watch today!
怖いよー！
That's scary!
船の事故って結構多いんだって！
I heard there are actually many boat accidents!
そうなんだー！
Is that so?
そう、だから海に入る以上、安全についても完璧に学ばないといけない！
Right, so since we're going out to sea, we must learn about safety perfectly!
ということで、今回はなんと、海上保安庁さんにご協力いただいております！
That's why this time, we have the cooperation of the Japan Coast Guard!
ええ？！海上保安庁？！
What?! The Japan Coast Guard?!
海の安全について、色々教えてくれるみたいなんで、早速行ってみよう！
They'll teach us about sea safety, so let's go!
ということで、今回ご協力いただく、秋山さんです！
So, Akiyama-san is cooperating with us today!
よろしくお願いします！
Thank you for having us!
よろしくお願いします。千葉海上保安部の秋山です。
Nice to meet you. I'm Akiyama from Chiba Coast Guard.
今日は一緒に勉強していきましょう！
Let's study together today!
おおー！よろしくお願いします！
Oh! We look forward to studying with you!
今日はなんと、船の運転にあたって、色々教えていただけると聞いたんですけど、よろしくお願いします！
Today, we heard you'd teach us about driving a boat, so thank you!
海を安全に楽しむためのポイントを
I would like to introduce the points for enjoying the sea safely
クイズを交えてご紹介させていただきたいと思います。
through some quizzes.
ちょっと待って、ミオしゃ聞いた？クイズだって…クイズやばいんですけど！
Wait, Mio-sha, did you hear? A quiz! Quizzes are bad...
ちょっと待って、でもうちは何も知らないよ？
Wait, I don't know anything about this!
もしかしてスバルだけが答えるってコト？
Is Subaru the only one answering?
なんで？一緒に協力しようっていう気は無いの？お前！
Why? Don't you want to cooperate with me, you?!
当事者意識！当事者意識！
Responsibility! Take some responsibility!
低めかもしれない…申し訳ないけど。
It might be low... I'm sorry about that.
ミスれねぇんだこれ…
I can't mess this up...
え、ミスれないの？
Oh, you can't?
え、ミスれないよ！スバルがちゃんと答えて、皆さんに伝えるってことですよね？つまり。
No, I can't! Subaru has to answer correctly and convey it to everyone, right?
はい、そうです。
Yes, that's right.
やべぇ！やべぇよ！
Oh no! This is bad!
それでは秋山さん、よろしくお願いします。
Well then, Akiyama-san, please go ahead.
よろしくお願いします。
Please.
日本の領土は約38万平方キロメートルで
Japan's territory is about 380,000 square kilometers,
世界で61番目の面積となっているんですけれども、
which ranks 61st in area in the world.
領土を囲む領海、
However, including the territorial waters surrounding the land
排他的経済水域を合わせると、
and the exclusive economic zone,
約447万平方キロメートル、
it is about 4.47 million square kilometers,
世界でも10位以内の広さとなっています。
which is within the top 10 in the world.
すごいじゃん！
That's amazing!
いや、だからさ、日本って島国じゃん！
I mean, Japan is an island country!
周りに海がいっぱいあるからってことですよね？
So it means there's a lot of sea around us, right?
そうです。
Yes, that's right.
海上保安庁はこの広大なエリアを
The Japan Coast Guard divides this vast area
11の管区に分けて、
into 11 regions,
海上保安官約15,000人で、
and with about 15,000 officers,
24時間365日守り続けています。
we protect it 24 hours a day, 365 days a year.
え！凄いよ！
Wow! That's amazing!
15,000人だけなんだよ？というか。
Only 15,000 people? I mean...
海上保安庁は少ない人数で頑張っているので、
The Japan Coast Guard is working hard with a small number of people,
スバルさん、
so Subaru-san,
よかったら、海上保安官になりませんか？
if you'd like, why don't you join us as a Coast Guard officer?
ええ？！
What?!
入っちゃおうかな！
Maybe I should join!
スカウトされてる！
She's being scouted!
ヤゴー、バイバイ！
YAGOO, bye-bye!
俺、海上保安官になる！
I'm going to be a Coast Guard officer!
大丈夫？大丈夫そうかな？結構ポンコツですよ？
Is that okay? Is she really okay? She's quite clumsy, you know?
忘れ物とか結構すごいんですけど大丈夫ですかね？
I forget things a lot, is that okay?
すぐ忘れちゃうんですけど。
I forget things easily.
どういう人が適性があるんですか？
What kind of person is suited for it?
確かに。
Indeed.
スバルさんのように真面目な方なら大丈夫です。
If they are serious like Subaru-san, it's fine.
えー！真面目なんだ！
Oh! She's serious!
次は、楽しいはずの海でのレジャーが
Next, to prevent fun marine leisure
悲しい事故にならないように、
from turning into sad accidents,
自分の命を救うための3つの基本を紹介します。
I will introduce three basics to save your life.
まず1つ目が、ライフジャケットの常時着用です。
First is wearing a life jacket at all times.
万が一、船から海に落ちてしまった場合、
In the unlikely event that you fall into the sea from a boat,
ライフジャケットを着用しているだけで、
just wearing a life jacket
着用していない人と比べると、助かる確率が
increases your chances of survival,
4倍にもなります。
by four times compared to those not wearing one.
おおー！すごい！
Oh! Amazing!
ですので、海でマリンレジャーを楽しむ際には、
So when enjoying marine leisure in the sea,
ライフジャケットの常時着用をお願いします。
please wear a life jacket at all times.
はい！
Yes!
ただし、ライフジャケットを正しく着用していても、
However, even if you wear a life jacket correctly,
脱げてしまったり、
it might come off,
古いものを使い続けていると、
or if you keep using an old one,
うまく膨らまなかったりしますので、
it may not inflate properly,
正しい着用と定期的な点検を心がけてくださいね。
so please ensure correct wear and regular inspection.
はい、分かりました！
Yes, understood!
次は、携帯電話等の連絡手段の確保です。
Next is securing communication methods such as mobile phones.
皆さんは普段の生活の中で、スマートフォンを持ち歩いていると思うんですけれども、
In your daily life, I think you usually carry a smartphone with you,
はい。
Yes.
海でもこれが非常に重要となります。
and this is also extremely important at sea.
おおー。
Ohh.
海での事故に遭ってしまった場合、
In the event of an accident at sea,
海上保安庁などの救助機関に、いち早く連絡することが重要なのですが、
contacting rescue agencies like the Japan Coast Guard as quickly as possible is crucial,
スマートフォンを海に落としてしまって、
but there are many cases where smartphones are dropped into the sea
通報できないということも多いため、
and cannot be used to report the incident,
このようにストラップ付きの防水パックで、
so carrying it in a waterproof case with a strap like this
持ち歩くことが大切なんです。
is very important.
へぇー！なるほど！
Wow! I see!
最後…
Lastly...
警察には110番
For the police, it's 110.
消防には119番といった番号と同様に
Just like 119 for the fire department,
海上保安庁にも緊急通報用の電話番号があるのですが、皆さんご存知ですか？
the Japan Coast Guard also has an emergency phone number. Does everyone know what it is?
えー！知らなかった、うちは！
Whoa, I didn't know that!
スバル知ってるこれ！
Subaru knows this one!
1級小型免許をお持ちのスバルさんなら、当然知っていると思います。
Since Subaru has a Class 1 boat license, she must know it, of course.
やばっ、圧やばい、圧やばい。
Oh no, the pressure is real...
海の事件・事故は、118番！
For emergencies and accidents at sea, dial 118!
すごいです！正解です！
Amazing! That is correct!
ここからは本格的に何問かクイズを出題していきたいと思います。
From here on, let's dive into the actual quiz questions!
やばい！さっきの序章だったんだって！
Oh my gosh, that was just the intro?!
え！そうなの！？がっつりクイズかと思ってたら。
Really?! I thought that was the main quiz!
これから海に出るスバルさんに、海上交通のルールについて質問です。
For Subaru, who is about to head out to sea, here is a question about maritime traffic rules.
はい！
Yes!
こちらにスバルさんが操船している船と、右側にミオさんが乗っている船があります。
Here is the boat Subaru is piloting, and on the right is the boat Mio is on.
このままではぶつかってしまう恐れがあるため、スバルさんが取るべき行動は次のうちどれでしょう。
At this rate, there's a risk of collision. Which of the following actions should Subaru take?
むー。
Hmm...
ミオちゃんわかるわけ？この距離感だったら急げば行ける！みたいな感じになりそうじゃない？
Mio, do you know? With this distance, wouldn't it feel like "I can make it if I speed up"?
ふはっ！そんなわけはないのだ！
Ahaha! No way!
なんだそのふはははは。
What's with that laugh?
これスバルね、これね、船舶免許で勉強したことある！これ知ってるよ！
Subaru studied this for her boat license! I know this!
そうお、そうだよね。
Oh, right, of course.
これは、4番！右に舵を切り、相手を避けるです！
The answer is number 4! Starboard steering to avoid the other boat!
正解は、4番です！
The correct answer is number 4!
このような状況では、海上衝突予防法という法律によって、
In this scenario, under the Act on Preventing Collisions at Sea,
相手を右側に見る船舶が、相手を避ける必要があるんです。
the vessel that sees the other on its starboard side must yield.
この場合はスバルさんの船が、右に舵を切って避けるか、
In this case, Subaru's boat must steer to starboard to yield,
減速、または停止してミオさんの船を避けるのが正解になります。
or slow down/stop to let Mio's boat pass.
スバルこういうときも怖いから止まっちゃいます、先にいってくださいって。
In real life, I'd get scared and just stop, saying "Please go ahead!"
あー、でも止まってもいいってことですもんね。そうです。
Ah, but stopping is also a valid option, right? Yes, it is.
次の問題！
[Next Question!]
ここに架空の湾、スバル湾があります。
Here we have a fictional bay called Subaru Bay.
船が入港するために、スバル航路を通って入港します。
To enter the port, ships travel through the Subaru Fairway.
航路のここに設置される航路標識の組み合わせを、この中からお答えください。
Please choose the correct combination of fairway markers to be placed here.
船舶免許持ってるのでわかります！
I have a license, so I know this!
これは、右舷標識と左舷標識なので、
These are the starboard and port hand markers.
赤い三角形の方が右で、
So the red triangle marker goes on the right,
緑の四角の方が左側に入ります。で、上も同じように入ります。
and the green square one goes on the left. It's the same for the top pair.
スバルさん、さすがです！
Impressive as always, Subaru!
よっしゃー！あぶねー。ちゃんと分かってた！
Awesome! Whew... She actually knew it!
次の問題！
[Next Question!]
ここに、航路標識を設置して、船に対して、
We place a marker buoy here to show ships...
標識の西側は安全に走れますよということを示したいのですが、その場合この4つのうちどれを設置すればいいと思いますか？
...that the waters to its west are safe. Which of these four markers should we use?
やばいよミオちゃん、これはちょっと難しいよ。
Oh no, Mio... This is actually a bit tough.
うちは全然さっぱり！0％分かりませんけど！
I have absolutely no clue! Zero percent!
えーでも、たぶん、一番右のやつだった気がします。
But I think it might be the one on the far right.
え、その心は？
Oh? What's your reasoning?
その心は、なんか一番右に置いてあるやつが西なんだよ。
My reasoning is that the one on the far right means west.
で、上上ってなってるやつが北で、下下が南で、
The pointing-up cones mean north, the pointing-down mean south,
ダイヤマークになってるやつが東なんじゃないかと思って。
and the diamond-shaped one means east, I think.
なるほど、方角を表してるってこと？
I see, so they represent cardinal directions?
そう！だから、たぶん、一番右！
Yes! So, probably the far right one!
スバルさん、正解です！
Subaru, you are correct!
あぶなーい！ちゃんと分かってるじゃん！
Phew, close call! You really know your stuff!
もう海上保安庁さんで間違えたら免許剥奪されちまう！
If I got it wrong in front of the Coast Guard, they'd revoke my license!
この航路標識は、方位標識と呼ばれるもので、
These fairway markers are called cardinal marks,
それぞれの標識の東西南北側に安全に走れる場所があるということを示しています。
indicating that safe-to-navigate waters lie on that respective side (N, S, E, or W).
本格的なクイズで海難防止について勉強していきましたが、船の事故についてもご紹介させてください。
We've learned about marine safety through these quizzes, but now let's look at some boat accident statistics.
令和7年に海上保安庁が取り扱った船の事故は1,711隻であり、
In 2025, the Coast Guard handled 1,711 vessel accidents.
そのうち、約半数の833隻がプレジャーボートでの事故となっています。
Of those, roughly half—833 vessels—were pleasure boat accidents.
プレジャーボートって何？
What is a pleasure boat?
なんかスバルの乗れる、すごいみんなで遊んだりとかするやつ、釣りしたりとか。
Like the kind Subaru can pilot, meant for recreation or fishing.
あー、観光用の船みたいな？
Ah, like a boat for sightseeing?
そう。
Yes.
この事故のうち約7割が、船の整備不良や見張り不十分といった、
Around 70% of these accidents were caused by human factors,
人為的要因と呼ばれる事故となっているんです。
such as poor maintenance or insufficient lookouts.
プレジャーボートを操船する方は、出航前点検、適切な見張りの実施を行い、事故を未然に防ぎましょう。
Boaters should conduct pre-departure checks and proper lookouts to prevent accidents.
はい！
Yes!
出航前点検の実施は、プレジャーボートの事故では、エンジン機器故障が多くを占めているんです。
As for pre-departure checks, engine/machinery failure accounts for a huge chunk of pleasure boat accidents.
船が動かなくなったことによって流されて、浅瀬に乗り上げてしまったり、
If a boat loses power, it can drift and run aground on shallows,
他の船にぶつかって、二次災害に繋がることもあることから、出航前点検は必ず実施して、船を適切に管理しましょう。
or collide with other vessels, leading to secondary disasters. Always check before you leave.
はい！
Yes!
そして見張りの実施が、安全運行の基本です。
And keeping a proper lookout is the basic foundation of safe boating.
海は広く、他の船とぶつかってしまう恐れはないと思われがちなのですが、
While you might think the ocean is wide enough that you won't collide with anyone,
見張り不十分による船同士の衝突は、多く発生しているんです。
collisions between vessels due to poor lookouts are actually very common.
船長だけではなく、ミオさんのように船に乗っている人たちにも、
Not just the captain, but also passengers like Mio
常に見張りを行って、事故を防いでください。
should always stay alert to prevent accidents.
ウチも見てなきゃいけないってコト？
Does that mean I also have to keep watch?
当たり前じゃん！
Of course!
死にたくなかったら見張りしてないとさ！
If you don't wanna die, you have to keep watch!
おええ！
Woah!
でも見張りは本当に大事ってめちゃめちゃ言われたから！え、めっちゃ大事ですよね？
But they really emphasized that keeping watch is super important! It is very important, right?
はい、とても大切です。
Yes, it is very important.
見張りの基本は全方位にわたり、
The basics of keeping watch are covering all directions,
対象物を特定せず、継続的に繰り返して行うことが重要です。
not focusing on specific objects, and doing it continuously and repeatedly.
うーん！
I see!
じゃあウチも見張り…頑張ります！
Then I will also... do my best keeping watch!
頑張ってね！
Do your best!
ということで！今回ご協力いただいた海上保安庁の秋山さん！
And with that! From the Japan Coast Guard who helped us today, Akiyama-san!
ありがとうございました！本当にありがとうございました！
Thank you very much! Thank you so much!
ありがとうございました。いっぱい釣れるといいですね。行ってらっしゃい！
Thank you very much. I hope you catch a lot. Have a safe trip!
行ってきます！いっぱい釣るぞ！
We're off! We'll catch a lot!
ということで、乗船しました！
And with that, we've boarded the boat!
え、こ、これがスバルの船…？
W-Wait, this is Subaru's boat...?
そう、これがスバルの船らしいです。なんか結構デカくてビビてます！
Yeah, apparently this is Subaru's boat. It's quite big, so I'm scared!
いや、デカくてビビってるってことはこれレンタルだよね？多分。
Wait, if you're scared because it's big, then it's a rental, right? Probably.
いや、そうだよ。これレンタルさせていただきました。
Yeah, that's right. We rented this.
今回はですね、セントラルさんの「東京湾フィッシング」に参加します。わあー！
This time, we are participating in Central's 'Tokyo Bay Fishing' plan. Wow!
木更津沖から気軽に楽しめるフィッシングプランで、
It's a fishing plan where you can easily enjoy off Kisarazu,
なんとね、ベテランスタッフさんのサポートを受けながらボートフィッシングが楽しめるということで、
and surprisingly, you can enjoy boat fishing with support from veteran staff!
それは安心だね！
That's reassuring!
ところがどっこい！普段はですね、スタッフさんが操縦するんですけど、
But wait! Usually, the staff operates the boat, but...
今回は許可をいただいたので、スバルが運転します！
since we got permission this time, Subaru will be driving!
ええー！？
What?!
え、え、それはでもあの、釣りをするってことだよね？
W-Wait, but that means we're going fishing, right?
そうだよ、今日は釣りをします。
Yeah, we're fishing today.
なんかポイントとか分かってるわけ？
Do you even know where the fishing spots are?
分かんない！だからね、スタッフさんに教えてもらおうと思う。
Nope! So, I'll have the staff teach me.
なるほどね。
I see.
ちなみに今回はね、シロギスっていうのを釣るらしい。聞いたことある？
By the way, apparently we are catching Japanese sillago this time. Ever heard of it?
え、ない。
No, I haven't.
入れ食いらしい！
Apparently they bite like crazy!
入れ食い！？
Like crazy?!
信じてるぞ！
I'm putting my trust in you!
本当かな、それ。信じてるぞ、セントラルさん！
Is that really true? I trust you, Central-san!
まあ行ってみましょうよ！
Well, let's go!
はい！ということで、出発準備OK！ミオしゃ、準備はいいか？
Yes! So, preparation for departure is complete! Mio-sha, are you ready?
いつでも行くぞ！
Ready anytime!
それじゃ、大空スバル号、出航！出航！
Then, Oozora Subaru-go, set sail! Set sail!
行くぞ！いけるのか、本当に。まずゆっくり発進。
Let's go! Can you really do this? First, start slowly.
やべえ、軽い。
Oh crap, it's so light.
軽い…？
Light...?
やべえ、めっちゃ軽い！ちょっと待って！
Oh crap, it's super light! Wait a minute!
大丈夫だから！大丈夫だから！
It's okay! It's okay!
このままだと前方のアレに突っ込みそうな感じだけど、大丈夫？
At this rate, it feels like we're going to crash into that boat ahead. Are you okay?
左から回っていきます。そうですね。おお！
I'll go around from the left. I see. Oh!
やべえ、めっちゃ軽い。軽いと何か問題が？
Crap, it's super light. Is there a problem if it's light?
軽いと、ぎゅーんって加速する。なるほどね、うわあ！
If it's light, it accelerates suddenly. I see, wow!
なにこの揺れ！
What's with this shaking!
やべえ、すぐ30出るやん！やば！すごい！
Oh crap, it immediately hit 30 knots! Crazy! Amazing!
めっちゃ曲がる。
It turns so much.
操縦しやすいってこと？
Does that mean it's easy to steer?
ちょっと慣れないかも！慣れてない。でも慣れていく。
I might not be used to it! Not used to it. But I'll get used to it.
やべえ！ゆっくり。死にたくなかったら見張っててくれ！
Oh crap! Slow down. If you don't want to die, keep watch!
なんか前方にデカいのが浮いてる。デカいのが浮いてる？
Something big is floating ahead. Something big is floating?
うん、何か浮いてる。何あれ。
Yeah, something is floating. What is that?
前のさ、船がいるじゃん。はい。
You see that boat ahead? Yes.
あの船がさ、同じ方向に行こうとしてるんだけどさ。確かにね。
That boat is trying to go in the same direction. True.
船の後ろも行っちゃダメだからさ、追い抜いた方がいいんだけど、スバルにそんな度胸はない。
You shouldn't go directly behind another boat either, so it's better to overtake it, but Subaru doesn't have that kind of courage.
うわあ！すげえ曲がる！すげえ曲がる！
Wow! It turns so much! It turns so much!
海運転ムズい！
Steering on the sea is hard!
持ってかれる？
Is it drifting?
よく分かんない方に曲がる。
It turns in directions I don't understand.
潮の流れとかがあるのかな。
Maybe there's a tide current or something.
でも確かに、スバル今までこんなに波立ってるところでこんなデカいの運転したことないかも。
But true, Subaru has never driven such a big boat in such wavy waters before.
意外と波は立ってるんですか？船長。
Are the waves actually quite high, Captain?
体感だいぶ立ってますね、これ。あ、そうなんだ。
Visually, they're pretty high. Oh, I see.
どう？スバル船長の運転は。
How is Captain Subaru's driving?
まだ不安はあるけど、この調子であれば、事故りはしなそう。
I'm still a bit anxious, but at this rate, it doesn't seem like we'll crash.
スバルビビりだからな。やばいってなったらエンジン止めるから。
Because Subaru is a scaredy-cat. If things get dangerous, I'll stop the engine.
エンジン切っちゃうんだ。うん、もう怖い。避けてくださいのスタンスでいくから。
So you'll just shut off the engine. Yeah, I'm scared. I'll take the stance of 'please avoid me'.
なるほどね。うおお！
I see. Woah!
多分スピード出した方が揺れ少ない気がする。それはそう！
I feel like it shakes less if we speed up. That's true!
それはそうなんだけどさ！あの船を抜かすまでは何があるか分からん。
That might be true, but! Until we pass that boat, we don't know what will happen.
いや、なんかこの間通る系苦手なんだよ、マジで。心理ストレスがやばい。
Seriously, I'm bad at passing through tight spaces like this. The mental stress is insane.
え、なんかあの船あそこ曲がろうとしている気がする。確かに、右側にちょっとずつ。
Wait, I feel like that boat is trying to turn there. Indeed, bit by bit to the right.
そうだよね。
Right.
いや、どうですか？初海。
So, how is your first time on the sea?
怖い。怖い？
Scary. Scary?
てか、こんなにいっぱい船がいる場所知らない。俺今まで家の庭でずっと走ってたやん。
Well, I didn't know there were places with so many boats. Until now, I've just been running around in my own yard.
じゃあ結構緊張感あるね。緊張感あるよ！
Then you must be feeling pretty tense. Of course I am!
ミオしゃ、あれ！うん。あれ、さっき習ったやつ！
Mio-sha, look at that! Yeah. That's what we just learned!
あー、あれ！ブイ！ブイ、ブイ。
Ah, that! A buoy! Buoy, buoy.
あれよ、海上保安庁さんがつけてくれてるんよ。お前ありがとう。ありがとうございました。
That's the one the Coast Guard placed for us. Thank you. Thank you very much.
おお、海に出る！おお！
Oh, we're out on the sea! Oh!
やべえ、ガチで海じゃん！ちょっと待って、やばすぎ。
Oh crap, it's seriously the open sea! Wait a minute, this is insane.
海だ！海じゃん。
It's the sea! It really is.
こんだけ広かったら安心感あるんじゃない？あるある！
If it's this wide, doesn't it feel safer? Yeah, totally!
初めてこんなレーダーみたいなの見たわ。おお！
This is my first time seeing a radar-like screen like this. Oh!
あの辺じゃね？お、この辺だ。
Isn't it around there? Oh, it's around here.
ポイント到着！
[Arrived at the spot!]
もういいのかな、始めて。始めて。いくぞ！フィッシュオン！ひょー！
Can we start now? Start. Let's go! Fish on! Wheee!
それで、底に着くのを待つ。
And then, wait for it to hit the bottom.
あ、着いた！トンって感じした。あとはズルズルと引きずる。
Ah, it hit! I felt a tap. Next, we slowly drag it.
するとシロギスというのが釣れるらしい。
And then, apparently, you can catch Japanese whiting.
本当かなぁ？
Is that true?
なんか突かれてる感覚あるよ！
I feel like something's poking at it!
本当？
Really?
なんかツンツンされてる。
It's getting pecked at.
これ餌だけ食われてねぇかな？
I wonder if they're just eating the bait.
どうなんだろうね。
I wonder.
シロギスって頭いいのかな？
Are Japanese whiting smart?
食い逃げされてたらどうしよう。
What if they're just dine-and-dashing?
でも小っちゃいから脳みそこっちんじゃないの？
But they're small, so isn't their brain tiny?
ミオしゃ刺すね～！
Miosha, that's brutal!
ちなみにアジ釣りに行った時はさ、
By the way, when I went horse mackerel fishing,
波と同化しろって言われたよ。
they told me to become one with the waves.
海と一体化したら釣れた！
And when I integrated with the sea, I caught one!
じゃあ今日も波と一体化しなよ！早く！
Then integrate with the waves today too! Hurry!
分かってるよそんなの！
I know that already!
お！来たかも！
Oh! I think it's coming!
来たか？来たか？来たか？
Is it here? Is it here? Is it here?
来てるんじゃない？引いてるよ！
Isn't it on? It's pulling!
来てないわ～。
It's not on~.
来てなかった。スバルも一回確認してみよ！
It wasn't. Let me check mine too!
なんか赤い紐ついてる。
There's some red string attached...
お！来た！
Oh! It's here!
来た来た来た来た！釣れてる釣れてる！
It's here, it's here! You got it, you got it!
釣れてるよ！来た！うわー！
You caught one! Yes! Wow!
ミオちゃん釣れるぞここ！
Mio-chan, you can catch them here!
本当に？
Really?
やっぱり海と一体化することなんや！
I knew it, becoming one with the sea is the key!
今一体化してた...？
Was I integrated just now...?
してたしてた！
Yes you were, yes you were!
やべぇ、釣り好きだわ。ホロライブ釣り部、結成しようかな、勝手に。
Man, I love fishing. Maybe I'll start a Hololive Fishing Club on my own.
釣り部。
Fishing Club.
これ砂の、砂の感じがクンクン来てるのか...
Is this... is it hitting the sand? Feeling the sand...
いや私もさ、これ砂かなとか思って、わかんねえなと思ってたら...
Yeah, I was also thinking, "Is this sand?" and not knowing...
お！来たかも！
Oh! I think it's coming!
来てんじゃない？
Isn't it on?
なんかグイってなった気がする。
I felt a tug.
お！来てるって！ミオちゃん頑張って！
Oh! It's on! Mio-chan, go for it!
マジで？
Seriously?
マジか！本当に？でもなんか軽くなったかも。
Seriously? Really? But it might have gotten lighter.
あ！来てる！
Ah! It's here!
来た来た来た！やったー！やったー！
It's here, it's here! Yay! Yay!
ほら、海と一体化するのが大事だったんだって！
See, I told you becoming one with the sea is important!
取れたー！
I got it!
ミオちゃんもう一匹釣ろうぜ！
Mio-chan, let's catch one more!
うん、頑張りたいね！
Yeah, I want to try my best!
どうしよう、釣りの案件来ちゃったら。
What if we get a fishing-related sponsor deal?
釣りの案件。
A fishing sponsor deal.
え、やべ、来てるかも。
Oh, wait, I might have one.
来てる？
Is it?
来てるか？これ。逃げられちゃったかな？でもなんか引いてる？
Is it? Did it get away? But it's pulling a bit?
上げてみないと意外とわかんなくない？
You don't really know until you reel it in, right?
私も途中まで... お！
I also, until halfway... Oh!
２匹！２匹ついてる！
Two! There are two of them!
２匹ついてる！２匹ついてる！２匹ついてます！
There are two! There are two! Two are on!
釣れてるような、釣れてないようなとか言ってたら２匹釣れてる。
I was like, "Is there one, is there not?" and it turned out to be two!
うまそう！
Looks delicious!
え、やべ、釣れてるかも。やべえ、えぐい、釣れてる！
Wait, I think I got one. Oh my, this is crazy, I got one!
ほら！釣れてる！本当だ、釣れてる、すごい！
Look! It's on! You're right, it's on, amazing!
来てる気がする... どうだ？どうだ？
I feel like I have one... How is it? How is it?
来てない...
It's not on...
おしい！
So close!
あとなんか魚って意外に殺気感じ取るらしい。
And apparently, fish are surprisingly good at sensing bloodlust.
じゃあウチは殺気が強いってこと？
So that means I have strong bloodlust?
たしかに。
True.
「絶対に釣ってやる」っていう。
Like, "I am absolutely going to catch you!"
なるほどね。
I see.
ミオちゃん、今何考えてるの？
Mio-chan, what are you thinking about right now?
え、今？
Huh, right now?
うん。
Yeah.
釣って、なんか無だな。
Fishing is... like "emptiness".
いや、そうだよ。これ無になりにみんな来てんだよ。
No, exactly. Everyone comes here to enter a state of emptiness.
そうなの？
Is that so?
なんか海見てぼーっとするついでに魚釣ってんだよ、これ。
You just stare blankly at the sea, and happen to catch fish on the side.
そうなんだ。
I see.
デジタルデトックスにはもってこいやね。
It's perfect for a digital detox.
でしょ？
Right?
波のリズムに身を任せる。
Surrender yourself to the rhythm of the waves.
そうだ、波のリズムに身を任せる。
That's right, surrender to the rhythm of the waves.
来た！
It's here!
来た！来てる、来てる、絶対来てると思う、これは、多分。どうだ？
It's here! It's on, it's on, I'm sure it's on, probably. How is it?
来てる来てる来てる！来た来た！ミオちゃん！やったー！
It's on, it's on, it's on! It's here, it's here! Mio-chan! Yay!
やったー！
Yay!
ミオちゃん２匹目！今の気持ちをどうぞ！
Mio-chan's second one! Please tell us how you feel!
嬉しいです！
I'm happy!
やったー！
Yay!
ピチピチです！
It's fresh and lively!
もう一回くらいエントリーしたら帰るか。
Shall we head back after one more attempt?
早っ！
So soon!
どう？ミオちゃん、体力的に。
How are you doing, Mio-chan? Energy-wise.
いや、全然大丈夫だけど。
Oh, I'm completely fine.
本当？
Really?
走ってるときより楽だわ。
This is much easier than when we're running.
ふざけんなよ、そんなの！
Don't say that!
スバルの大空クルーズが良くないみたいじゃないか！
You're making it sound like Subaru's Oozora Cruise was bad!
今日はね、これ釣った魚食べられるから。
Today, we can eat the fish we catch.
キスってさ、どういう種類の食べ方思い浮かぶ？
When you think of whiting, what kind of dishes come to mind?
え、天ぷらじゃない？
Eh, tempura, right?
やっぱ天ぷらかな？
As expected, tempura?
お刺身もいけるんだって！
Apparently, you can also have it as sashimi!
魚屋からってこと？
You mean from a fishmonger?
ミオちゃん、次のさ、大空クルーズの生贄選んで。
Mio-chan, pick the next sacrificial victim for Oozora Cruise.
ええー？
Eeeh?
船酔いしなさそうで、楽しんでくれそうな人がいい？
Do you want someone who doesn't get seasick and seems like they'd enjoy it?
うん。
Yeah.
ちはとかは？
How about Chiha?
お！ちは良いじゃん！
Oh! Chiha is great!
ちはは絶対楽しんでくれるでしょ！
Chiha will definitely enjoy it!
絶対楽しんでくれそうなタイプ。
The type who would definitely enjoy it.
じゃあちはに一言！
Then, a message to Chiha!
意外と酔うから、絶対に酔い止めは飲んで来た方がいいよ。
It's surprisingly easy to get seasick, so you should definitely take seasick pills before coming.
ちはバイク乗ってる、バイクだっけ？車だっけ？
Chiha rides a motorcycle... was it a motorcycle? Or a car?
車！
Car!
酔わないんじゃないの？意外に。
Wouldn't she not get sick then, surprisingly?
えー、どうかなー？
Well, who knows?
ちは！来年乗ってくれよな！今年でも可！
Chiha! Ride with us next year! This year is fine too!
でもノリノリで来てくれそう。
But she'd probably come with lots of enthusiasm.
鬼ノリいいからな。
Yeah, she's super hyped.
でも莉々華とかも良さそう。
But Ririka also seems good.
莉々華はさ、なんかもう何が起きるか分かんないから...
Ririka, like, you never know what's going to happen with her...
なんか莉々華と行くんだったら、すげえの釣りに行きたいな。
If I'm going with Ririka, I'd want to go catch something crazy.
でもフブキもさ、めっちゃ釣り好きだからさ。
But Fubuki is also super into fishing.
そうなの！？
Really!?
そうだよ、だって事あるごとにゲーム内で釣りばっかしてるじゃん。
Yeah, she's always fishing in games every chance she gets.
いや確かに。あれゲームだからとかじゃなくて？
Indeed. But isn't that just because it's a game?
違うよ！
No!
でも確かに、釣りガチャ要素強いしな。
But true, fishing has a strong gacha element.
うん。
Yeah.
今日めっちゃ晴れてよかったね。
I'm so glad it's sunny today.
ね、すごいよ、こんなにバチバチに晴れて。
Yeah, it's amazing, it's so incredibly sunny.
るのー！
Is it on?!
おっ、釣れてんじゃない？
Oh, isn't there something on?
どうだどうだ？どうだ？重い気がする！
How is it? How is it? It feels heavy!
ミオちゃん、でかいの来てるんじゃないの？
Mio-chan, isn't a big one coming?
どうだどうだ？釣れたか？
How is it, how is it? Did I catch it?
釣れた！
I caught it!
やったー！
Yay!
やったー！うわ、シロギス！
Yay! Wow, a Japanese whiting!
元気いっぱいだ！
It's so energetic!
わ、クラゲだ！すごい、浮いてる。
Wow, a jellyfish! Amazing, it's floating.
本当だ。
You're right.
最近スバル、クラゲ食うのにハマってるから。
Recently, Subaru's been obsessed with eating jellyfish.
そうなの？持って帰る？
Really? Want to take it home?
いや、要らない…怖いもん。
No, I don't need it... they're scary.
刺されると痛ぇ。
It hurts if you get stung.
やべ、これ釣れてる、多分。
Shoot, I think I caught one.
来てるか？
Is it coming?
引いてる、引いてる。これは絶対釣れてる。
It's pulling, it's pulling. I definitely caught one.
ほら！キター！
Look! It's here!
キタ！やったー！
It's here! Yay!
ミオちゃん、俺がエントリーしたい！
Mio-chan, I want to cast the line!
いいよ。
Sure.
行くよ。いち、
Here I go. One,
にの、
Two,
さん！
Three!
おせえ…
Too slow...
いいの！「の」言うの忘れたなって今。
It's fine! I realized I forgot to say "no" just now.
果たして釣れるのか。
Will we actually catch anything?
はい。「ちょん」としました！あとはミオちゃん頑張って。
Alright. I gave it a twitch! Now do your best, Mio-chan.
「ちょん」ってするの分かるんだ！
You can tell when it does a twitch!
うん。
Yeah.
お、引いてる？あ、引いてる？嘘、あ、本当だ！
Oh, is it pulling? Ah, is it pulling? No way, ah, it really is!
引いてる、引いてる！
It's pulling, it's pulling!
引いてる、引いてる！なんか引いてるかも！ゆっくりゆっくり、ゆっくり、なんか引いてるかも！
It's pulling, it's pulling! Something might be pulling!
頑張れ！
Do your best!
おいしょ、うわ！キタ！
Here we go, wow! It's here!
キター！
It's here!
ラストフィッシング！やったー！
Last fishing! Yay!
ラストフィッシングや！
It's the last fishing!
ということで！本日釣れた釣果がこちら！
And so! Here is our catch of the day!
わー！
Wow!
ね、すごいや、ミオちゃんマジで。
See, that's amazing, Mio-chan, seriously.
すごい、いっぱい釣れたね。
Amazing, we caught a lot.
14匹釣れてんだよ、やば！
We caught 14 of them, crazy!
ということでミオちゃん、釣ったやつ、すぐ食べたいと思わないか？
So, Mio-chan, don't you want to eat what we caught right away?
おー！た、食べられるんですか？生は無理だよ、うち。
Oh! C-Can we eat them? I can't do raw.
いやいや、生でいけとは言ってないよ、別に。
No, no, I didn't say to eat it raw.
このままはちょっと踊り食いはね、狼と言えど！
Eating them alive like this is a bit too much, even for a wolf!
これからこれを料理して、食べたいと思います！
We're going to cook this now and eat it!
ということで、さっき釣った魚がこちらです！
So, here is the fish we caught earlier!
え、すごい！もう面影ない！
Eh, amazing! There's no trace of how they looked before!
いや、そうだよ。完全にない。
I know, right. Absolutely none.
ということでね、釣った後はやっぱ、釣りたての魚を食べるのが醍醐味！
So, after fishing, the real pleasure is eating freshly caught fish!
うわ、贅沢！
Wow, so luxurious!
食べようぜ！
Let's eat!
せーの、いただきます！
Ready, set, let's eat!
何から食べる？
What should we eat first?
え、お刺身でしょ！
Eh, the sashimi, right?
お刺身にできるぐらいのでかいやつって珍しいらしいよ。
Apparently, ones big enough to make sashimi out of are quite rare.
そうなの？
Is that so?
いただきます。
Let's eat.
いただきます。うわ、すごい！
Let's eat. Wow, amazing!
ミオちゃんが釣ったやつだよ、それ。
That's the one you caught, Mio-chan.
本当？
Really?
適当パチこいてんだろ！
You're just making stuff up, right?
いやいや、何でそんなこと言うの！
No, no, why would you say that!
ミオちゃんが釣ったやつかもしれないじゃん。
It could be the one you caught.
分かんないだろ。いただきまーす！
There's no way to know. Let's eat!
美味しい！
Delicious!
うん、歯応えがある。
Mmm, it has a nice chew to it.
甘い！
Sweet!
甘い！結構噛み応えがしっかりしてて甘いね。
Sweet! It's quite firm and sweet.
見て、プリプリ。すごい肉厚だ、結構。
Look how plump it is. It's really thick-cut.
普通のお刺身ではない。
This isn't like normal sashimi.
いや、ないでしょ。そうなんだよ、釣りたてのお刺身は美味しいんだよ。
Of course not. That's right, freshly caught sashimi is so good.
釣りたてってなんかやっぱ違うよね。
Freshly caught really is different, isn't it?
天ぷらも食べよう。テンポンテンポン。
Let's eat the tempura too. Tempong, tempong.
いただきます。
Let's eat.
うーん！うま！
Mmm! Delicious!
うま！
Delicious!
これは美味しい。
This is delicious.
でしょ！でしょってスバルが作ったわけじゃないんですけど。作っていただいたんですけど。最高です。
Right! Not that I made it, though. We had it made for us. But it's the best.
ミオちゃんどうだった？大空クルーズ星３って言ってたやん。
How was it, Mio-chan? You gave Oozora Cruise 3 stars.
なんと今ならこのプロの人が作ったご飯付き！
And now, it comes with a meal made by a professional!
そんなん星５になるに決まってる！
That easily makes it 5 stars!
いぇーい！
Yay!
それではこのご飯を食べながら、最後はさよならしたいと思うんですけど。
So, while eating this meal, I'd like to say goodbye for the end.
お、もうさよならのお時間なんですか？
Oh, is it already time to say goodbye?
そうだよ。今日は海上保安庁さん行ってさ。いやそうだよ、朝からさ。
That's right. Today we visited the Japan Coast Guard. Yeah, since the morning.
超早朝からさ、行ってさ、ルール教えてもらってさ。
We went there super early, and they taught us the rules.
大空クルーズが出航してさ、釣りしてさ、これ作ってもらってさ。
The Oozora Cruise set sail, we went fishing, and had this made for us.
ちょっと聞いてる？食べてるけど。
Are you listening? You're just eating.
それじゃあ、大空クルーズ、これにて第一部、終！
Well then, Oozora Cruise, with this, Part 1 is finished!
じゃあみんな、またねー！
See you all later!
バイバーイ！バイバイ！
Bye-bye! Bye-bye!
またのご来店…じゃあないわ。ご来場？何て言うの？
Hope to see you again... wait, no. Visit? What do you say?
ご…船に乗れ！バイバイ！
Vi... get on the boat! Bye-bye!
バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!